Guide to the Paula Kamen Papers, 1970-2006 and undated (bulk 1991-2002) RL.00765
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paula Kamen papers
1970-2006 and undated, bulk 1991-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kamen, Paula
RL.00765
57 Linear Feet
Paula Kamen was born in Chicago and grew up in Flossmoor, Illinois. She received a bachelor's degree in journalism in 1989 from the University of Illinois. Kamen is a Chicago-based (current as of 2007) journalist, playwright, and the author of a number of books, including one of the first books to describe the third wave of feminism. Articles and book reviews by Kamen have been published in The New York Times, Washington Post, Ms., Chicago Tribune, among others, and more than a dozen anthologies. Kamen is also a frequent public speaker and has appeared at over 70 universities. A focus of the collection, which spans the years 1971-2006, is on Generation X women, feminism, and sexuality. Contains a Writings Series which includes research files, drafts, and publicity-related files for all of Kamen's major works as of 2006, as well as drafts of and materials related to articles and other shorter pieces written by Kamen. Works represented are the nonfiction books All In My Head: An Epic Quest to Cure an Unrelenting, Totally Unreasonable, and Only Slightly Enlightening Headache, Feminist Fatale: Voices from the Twentysomething Generation Explore the Future of the Women's Movement, Her Way: Young Women Remake the Sexual Revolution, and the plays Jane: Abortion and the Underground and Seven Dates with Seven Writers. Other series in the collection are Conferences and Engagements, with files relating to Kamen's frequent speaking engagements, particularly at universities; Subject Files, an extensive array of clippings and articles maintained by Kamen on a wide range of feminist subjects primarily in the 1990s; Audiovisual Materials, and Printed Materials.
30,000 Items
Access Restrictions
Portions of this collection are not open to research until 2057. Restricted materials consist of personal interviews conducted by Kamen which are in an audio format and correspondence related to All In My Head: An Epic Quest to Cure an Unrelenting, Totally Unreasonable, and Only Slightly Enlightening Headache. Additionally, researchers are asked not to quote the names of non-activist individuals quoted within the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Paula Kamen Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2004.
Biographical Note
Paula Kamen was born in Chicago and grew up in Flossmoor, Illinois. She received a bachelor's degree in journalism in 1989 from the University of Illinois. Kamen is a Chicago-based (current as of 2007) journalist, playwright, and the author of a number of books, including one of the first books to describe the third wave of feminism. Articles and book reviews by Kamen have been published in The New York Times, Washington Post, Ms., Chicago Tribune, among others, and more than a dozen anthologies. Kamen is also a frequent public speaker and has appeared at over 70 universities.
Collection Overview
The Paula Kamen Papers span the years 1970-2006, with the bulk of the material dating from 1991 to 2002. The collection documents Kamen's career as a writer and journalist. Specific topics covered by Kamen and addressed in the collection are Generation X women, feminism, and sexuality, abortion, popular culture, and chronic pain. The collection is organized into five series: Writings, Conferences and Engagements, Subject Files, Audiovisual Materials, and Printed Materials.
The Writings Series includes research files, drafts, and publicity-related files for all of Kamen's major works as of 2006, as well as drafts of and materials related to articles and other shorter pieces written by Kamen. The Other Files subseries primarily includes correspondence related to the publishing of Kamen's writings, and also contains pieces in which Kamen is cited. Works represented in the Writings Series are the nonfiction books All In My Head: An Epic Quest to Cure an Unrelenting, Totally Unreasonable, and Only Slightly Enlightening Headache, Feminist Fatale: Voices from the Twentysomething Generation Explore the Future of the Women's Movement, Her Way: Young Women Remake the Sexual Revolution, and the plays Jane: Abortion and the Underground and Seven Dates with Seven Writers.
Materials in the Conferences and Engagements Series document Kamen's frequent speaking engagements at college and university campuses, bookstores, and conferences throughout the 1990s. A significant number of these talks were in support of her books Feminist Fatale and Her Way.
The Subject Files Series contains files maintained by Kamen on a wide range of subjects pertaining to her writing interests. Topics covered in this series include feminism, activism, politics, popular culture, and sex, along with many others. These files consist primarily of clippings from magazines, newspapers, and other publications.
The Audiovisual Materials Series contains audio cassettes, micro cassettes, compact discs, videotapes, and photographs. A majority of these materials are recordings of interviews conducted by Kamen during the course of researching her books and articles. Other recordings are from conferences attended by Kamen, a production of Kamen's play, Seven Dates with Seven Writers, and copies of television programs which included appearances by Kamen. Photographic material consists of photographs taken at the 1993 March on Washington for Lesbian and Gay Rights and at an undated production of Kamen's play, Seven Dates with Seven Writers.
Items in the Printed Materials Series consist of 20 issues of the magazines Deneuve and Curve. Other magazines and a number of zines are filed separately, with the Bingham Center's Women's, Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Movements Periodical Collection, and with the Bingham Center's Women's Zine Collection, respectively. A complete list of these titles may be found in the Items Separated section of this document.
Items Separated
The following magazines have been added to the Bingham Center's Women's and Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, and Transgender Movements Periodicals Collection. Please contact Research Services if you wish to use these items.
Anything That Moves, Issue 5, 1993
Ben Is Dead, October/November 1992
Changing Men, Issue 24, Summer/Fall 1992
Davika, Premiere Issue, Winter 1996
Davika, Volume 1, Number 2
Davika, Winter 1997
Fabula, Volume 4, Issue 1
Factsheet 5, No. 52
Factsheet 5, No. 59
Frighten the Horses, No. 7, 9, 12
Hues, Winter 1996
Hues, Winter 1996
Hues, Summer 1997
Hues, Winter 1997
Hues, Summer 1998
Hues, September-October 1998
Hues, Winter 1998
Hues, November-December 1998
Hues, January-February 1999
Hues, March-April 1999
Lambda Book Report, Volume 5, No. 1, July 1996
Lesbian Contradiction, Issue 44, Fall 1993
Libido, Volume 3, Number 4, Fall 1991
Libido, Volume 4, Number 1, Winter 1993
Libido, Volume 5, Number 3, Summer 1993
Ludus, February-March
Maxine, Issue No. 3, 4
Moxie, Spring 1999, Volume 2, No. 2, 3
National Times, Summer 2001, Volume 33, No. 2
NARAL Campus Newsletter, Volume 1, Number 2, Fall 1980
Off Our Backs, Volume 23, Number 8, August/September 1993
On Our Backs, September/October 1989
On Our Backs, January/February 1993
On Our Backs, May/June 1993
On Our Backs, July/August 1993
On Our Backs, September/October 1993
On Our Backs, August/September 2000
Pucker Up, Fall/Winter 2006, Volume 1, Issue 4
Rockrgrl, Issue 19, 20, 28
Sassy, February 1991, No. 35, 39, 41, 42, 45, 46, 48-50, 52-54, 61, 65, 66
Sassy, September 1995
Sassy, October 1995
Sassy, November 1995
Sassy, December 1995
Sassy, March 1996
See It? Tell It. Change It!, Spring/Summer 1998
Venus, Winter 2002, No. 14
The following zines have been added to the Bingham Center's Women's Zines Collection. Please contact Research Services for assistance in using these items.
The Adventures of Anti-career Girl, Issue 1
Alien Religion
The Artless Hymnal
Bulldozer, Issue 1
Candy-ass, Spring/Summer 1996
Continuum, Spring 1994
Discharge, Number 4
Feminists For Cleavage
Free to Fight
Girl Fiend
I Hate You
Infected Faggot Perspectives, Issue 10
Infected Faggot Perspectives, Issue 14, Summer 1993
Junglegym, Catalog 1
Patriarchy Kills
Planet Girl, April 1993
Plotz, Issue 6, 10
The Propaganda, 1999-2000: The First Year of the Conspiracy
Queer Zine Explosion
Riveter, Issue 1, Spring 2002
Rollerderby, Issue 20, 1997
Speculum Veritas, Issue 4, Winter 1997/1998
Thrift Score, Issue 10
Untitled
The Urban Herbalist, No. 7, April 1993
Whose Feminism is it Anyway?
Womyn Who Masturbate, Issue 4, Spring 1993
Young women -- United States -- Social life and customs; Young women -- Sexual behavior -- United States; Abortion services -- Illinois -- Chicago -- Drama; American drama -- Women authors; Women college students -- United States -- Social life and customs; Women authors -- 20th century; Dating (Social customs) -- United States; Jane (Abortion service) -- Drama; Chronic diseases -- United States -- Personal narratives; Chronic pain -- Patients -- United States; Feminists -- United States; Feminism -- United States; Headache -- United States -- Personal narratives; Headache -- Patients -- United States; Theater -- United States -- 20th century; Pain -- United States -- Personal narratives; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Kamen, Paula; Kamen, Paula
- Writings Series, 1982-2005 and undated, 50 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in this series include research files, drafts, and publicity-related files for all of Kamen's major works as of 2006, as well as drafts of and materials related to articles and other shorter pieces written by Kamen. The Other Files subseries primarily includes correspondence related to the publishing of Kamen's writings, and also contains pieces in which Kamen is cited. Works represented in the Writings series are the nonfiction books All In My Head: An Epic Quest to Cure an Unrelenting, Totally Unreasonable, and Only Slightly Enlightening Headache (2005), Feminist Fatale: Voices from the Twentysomething Generation Explore the Future of the Women's Movement (1991), Her Way: Young Women Remake the Sexual Revolution (2000), and the plays Jane: Abortion and the Underground (1999) and Seven Dates with Seven Writers (1998). A significant number of drafts are present; some reflect different iterations of a work in progress, or segments thereof, and some incude comments and notations by Kamen and others. A large portion of the research conducted by Kamen for her works of nonfiction is in the form of interviews. Typed transcriptions of many of these interviews are included and are identified most often by the location in which the interviews were conducted. The collection contains many notebooks used by Kamen during her research but the handwriting is quite difficult to decipher. Wherever possible, original folder titles have been retained. The subseries are arranged alphabetically by major work, followed by Other Writings and Other Files.
  - All In My Head: An Epic Quest to Cure an Unrelenting, Totally Unreasonable, and Only Slightly Enlightening Headache, 2000-2004, 15 boxes
    All In My Head was written by Kamen to document her experiences in trying to cure her severe headache problems. By the time of publication, she had been battling what is now diagnosed as chronic daily headache for 15 years. Materials in this subseries are divided into drafts, publicity-related material, and research. Draft material is arranged by order in which the segment was to be included in the book, with chronological arrangement where applicable. Edited drafts appear in alphabetical order by name of the editor. Research files include transcribed interviews, notebooks, clippings, and materials from pain- and headache-related conferences attended by Kamen. Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Drafts
      - Outline, 2000, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Outline, 2002 (Box 1)
      - Outline, 2003, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - How to Cure an American Headache proposal, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - The Waiting Place proposal and preface (Box 1)
      - Proposal, 2002 May 8 (Box 2)
      - Proposal, 2002 May 30 (Box 2)
      - Preface, 2002 May 30 (Box 2)
      - Proposal, 2002 June 12 (Box 2)
      - Proposal, 2002 June 17 and 2002 June 24 (Box 2)
      - Proposal, 2002 June 26 and 2002 June 30 (Box 2)
      - Proposal, 2002 October 30 (Box 2)
      - Table of Contents, chapters 3-9 (Box 2)
      - Chapter 1, Big Pharma, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Chapters 1, 3, 4, January 2004 (Box 3)
      - Chapter 3, External Challenges (Box 3)
      - Side Effects (Box 3)
      - All In My Head?, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Sex and the Single Migraneur (Box 3)
      - Chapter 9, Recreational Medicine (Box 3)
      - Denial (Box 3)
      - Chapters 10, 13-15 (Box 4)
      - Mind/Wallet Connection (Box 4)
      - High Anxiety (Box 4)
      - New Generation (Box 4)
      - Conclusion outline (Box 4)
      - Conclusion/The Waiting Place, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Bibliography and acknowledgements (Box 4)
      - Corrections, 2004 (Box 5)
      - Draft, 2004 July 24, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Edited draft: Bridget (Box 5)
      - Edited draft: Marnie Cochran, 2004 March (Box 5)
      - Edited draft: Marnie Cochran, 2004 August, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Edited draft: Dad and Wendy (Box 6)
      - Edited draft: Kyra, 2004, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Edited draft: Elizabeth Loder, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Edited draft: Megan Shanks (Box 6)
      - Edited draft: Tamara, 2004 August, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 6)
      - Edited draft: Tamara, 2004 August, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 7)
    - Publicity
      - Correspondence, 4 folders (Box 7)
        [CLOSED]
      - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Speaking materials (Box 7)
      - Promotional poster (Box 7, Oversize-folder 138, Folder 1)
    - Research
      - American Headache Society conference, 2003 June (Box 8)
      - American Pain Society annual scientific meeting, 2003 March (Box 8)
      - American Society for Reproductive Medicine conference, 2003 October (Box 8)
      - Approaching Migraine as a Chronic Disease program, 2003 June (Box 8)
      - Articles, 2 folders (Box 8)
      - Center on Addiction and Substance Abuse (CASA) conference, 2003 February (Box 8)
      - Citations: books and articles (Box 8)
      - Clippings: headaches, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Depression conference, 2004 March (Box 9)
      - Ideas (Box 9)
      - Interview transcripts, Folders 1-4 of 6 (Box 9)
      - Interview transcripts, Folders 5-6 of 6 (Box 10)
      - Jack Kamen memoir, 6 folders (Box 10)
      - Newsletters and publications (Box 10)
      - Notebooks, Folders 1-7 of 8 (Box 11)
      - Notebooks, Folder 8 of 8 (Box 12)
      - Outlines, notes, and ideas (Box 12)
      - Pain group: memberships and conferences, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Pain group conference, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Quotes and notes (Box 12)
      - Releases (Box 13)
      - Tai chi exercise material (Box 13)
      - The Waiting Place (Box 13)
  - Feminist Fatale: Voices from the Twentysomething Generation Explore the Future of the Women's Movement, 1991-1997, 4 boxes
    Feminist Fatale is the first major work completed by Kamen and was published when she was only 24. Kamen interviewed young women throughout the United States regarding their views on feminism. Materials in this subseries are divided into drafts, publicity-related files, and research. There is a small amount of draft material, arranged alphabetically. Publicity-related material includes reviews and press releases and is arranged alphabetically. Research files are comprised primarily of transcribed interviews and clippings and are arranged alphabetically.
    - Drafts
      - Annotated draft, 1991 May 14 (Box 13)
      - Annotated draft, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Outline, chapters 1, 2, 4 (Box 13)
    - Publicity (Box 14)
      - Business (Box 14)
      - Press releases (Box 14)
      - Promotions and letters, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - Publicity, 1991-1997 (Box 14)
      - Reviews (Box 14)
      - Promotional poster (Box 14, Oversize-folder 138, Folder 1)
    - Research
      - Clippings, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Interview transcripts, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Notebooks, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - Rape/sexual assault, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Releases, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - Young Feminists (Box 16)
  - Her Way: Young Women Remake the Sexual Revolution, 1993-2001 and undated, 19 boxes
    In Her Way, Kamen interviewed over one hundred young women in the United States regarding their attitudes toward sex. This subseries has been divided into three sections: drafts, publicity, and research. Drafts are arranged chronologically and draft segments are arranged alphabetically by segment (or chapter) title. Publicity and research files are arranged alphabetically. Within research files, transcribed interviews are filed according to the geographic location where the interview was conducted.
    - Drafts
      - Preface-Part Three, 1997 April (Box 17)
      - Preface-Chapter 3, 1997 May (Box 17)
      - 1997 September 7, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Introduction-Chapter 5, 1997 October (Box 17)
      - Introduction-Superrats, 1997 October (Box 17)
      - 1997 October, Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 17)
      - 1997 October, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 18)
      - Chapter 6-Chapter 22, 1997 October-November, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - 1997 November 20 (Box 18)
      - 1997 November 24, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - 1997 November, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - 1997, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - 1999, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Final editing NYU, 2000 (Box 19)
      - Behavior and Attitudes, Folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 19)
      - Behavior and Attitudes, Folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 20)
      - Conclusion (Box 20)
      - Description/Synopsis (Box 20)
      - Family, 3 folders (Box 20)
      - Female Attitudes (Box 20)
      - His Way (Box 20)
      - Information, 4 folders (Box 21)
      - Introduction, Folders 1-4 of 5 (Box 21)
      - Introduction, Folder 5 of 5 (Box 22)
      - Lesbians (Box 22)
      - Living Single (Box 22)
      - Locker Room Talk, 2 folders (Box 22)
      - Morality (Box 22)
      - Segments with New York University Ed. Collection, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 22)
      - Segments with New York University Ed. Collection, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 23)
      - Permissive Male Values (Box 23)
      - Power and Permission (Box 23)
      - Preface (Box 23)
      - Religion, 3 folders (Box 23)
      - Safe Sex (Box 23)
      - Superrats, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - Table of Contents (Box 24)
      - Virgins, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Women's and Social Movements, 2 folders (Box 24)
      - Updates 2001 (Box 24)
    - Publicity
      - Book supports (Box 24)
      - Correspondence (Box 24)
      - Expenses (Box 24)
      - Permissions (Box 24)
      - Media sources (Box 24)
      - Publicity (Box 24)
      - Reviews (Box 25)
      - Sales (Box 25)
      - Promotional poster (Box 25, Oversize-folder 138, Folder 1)
    - Research
      - Anti-rape (Box 25)
      - Attitudes and double standards, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Austin, Texas, 1993, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Book Lists (Box 25)
      - California (Box 25)
      - Chicago, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Colleges (Box 26)
      - Conclusion (Box 26)
      - Conference at Hampshire [College], 1993, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Cultural (Box 26)
      - Family (Box 26)
      - Feminism (Box 26)
      - Feminist resources (Box 26)
      - Grants, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Health grants (Box 26)
      - MS Grant (Box 26)
      - Health Conference (Box 26)
      - Information (Box 27)
      - Initiation (Box 27)
      - Interviews (Box 27)
      - Lesbians (Box 27)
      - Lisa Dans (Box 27)
      - Locker Room Talk (Box 27)
      - Long Beach (Box 27)
      - Magazine articles, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - Massachusetts (Box 27)
      - Men and Sexperts (Box 27)
      - Morals (Box 28)
      - New Hampshire (Box 28)
      - New York, NY (Box 28)
      - New York and New Jersey interviews, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Notebooks, Folders 1-4 of 13 (Box 28)
      - Notebooks, Folders 5-10 of 13 (Box 29)
      - Notebooks, Folders 11-13 of 13 (Box 30)
      - Outline (Box 30)
      - Pornography (Box 30)
      - Pornography conference (Box 30)
      - Power and permission (Box 30)
      - Rape and sex (Box 30)
      - Religion (Box 31)
      - Religion, 1996 (Box 31)
      - Reproduction (Box 31)
      - Research: General, Folders 1-6 of 8 (Box 31)
      - Research: General, Folders 7-8 of 8 (Box 32)
      - Resistance (Box 32)
      - Safe sex (Box 32)
      - San Francisco, 2 folders (Box 32)
      - Santa Barbara (Box 32)
      - Scholarly articles (Box 32)
      - Sources (Box 33)
      - Student interviews (Box 33)
      - Studies/Surveys (Box 33)
      - Texas, 2 folders (Box 33)
      - Virgins and saying no (Box 33)
      - Women's studies conference (Box 33)
  - Jane: Abortion and the Underground, 1992-1999, 10 boxes
    Play based on the true story of an underground abortion service (known as Jane) that existed in Chicago from 1969 to 1973 and was run by students and housewives. Materials in this subseries are comprised of drafts, publicity-related material, and research. Drafts are arranged chronologically. Publicity-related files are arranged alphabetically and also includes material related to productions of the play. Research files contain clippings, interviews, and notebooks, and are arranged alphabetically.
    - Drafts
      - 1992 November 15 (Box 34)
      - 1992 November 17 (Box 34)
      - 1992 November 25 (Box 34)
      - 1992 November 30 (Box 34)
      - 1992 November 30 (Box 34)
      - 1992 December 5 (Box 34)
      - 1992 December 6 (Box 34)
      - 1992 December 10 (Box 34)
      - 1992 December 16, Folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 34)
      - 1992 December 16, Folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 35)
      - 1993 January 18 (Box 35)
      - 1993 January 28 (Box 35)
      - 1993 March 5 (Box 35)
      - 1993 April 29, 2 folders (Box 35)
      - 1993 June 21 (Box 35)
      - 1998 November-December (Box 35)
      - 1998 December 7, 1998 December 14 (Box 36)
      - 1998 December 14 (Box 36)
      - 1999 June 24 (Box 36)
      - 1999 July 2 (Box 36)
      - 1999 July 12 (Box 36)
      - 1999 September 30 (Box 36)
      - 1999 August 8 (Box 36)
      - Fragments, 3 folders (Box 36)
    - Publicity and Related Materials
      - Correspondence: play orders (Box 37)
      - Expenses (Box 37)
      - Laura Kaplan Jane book (Box 37)
      - Legal documents (Box 37)
      - Media coverage, 2 folders (Box 37)
      - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 37)
      - Theater productions (Box 38)
      - Theater productions: Green Highway (Box 38)
      - Promotional poster (Box 94)
    - Research
      - Abortion and health care (Box 38)
      - Chicago Maroon (Box 38)
      - Clippings, Folders 1-5 of 8 (Box 38)
      - Clippings, Folders 6-8 of 8 (Box 39)
      - Consent (Box 39)
      - Gag rule (Box 39)
      - General, Folders 1-4 of 10 (Box 39)
      - General, Folders 5-10 of 10 (Box 40)
      - Guilt, 2 folders (Box 40)
      - Interview transcripts, Folder 1 of 6 (Box 40)
      - Interview transcripts, Folders 2-6 of 6 (Box 41)
      - Notebooks, Folders 1-3 of 4 (Box 41)
      - Notebooks, Folder 4 of 4 (Box 42)
      - RU-486 (Box 42)
  - Seven Dates with Seven Writers, 1996-2002, 2 boxes